Guide to the Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Collection, 1876-2020 and undated, bulk 1950-2020 RL.10006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel collection
1876-2020 and undated, bulk 1950-2020
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Diamonstein-Spielvogel, Barbaralee
RL.10006
654 boxes 654 boxes; 8 oversize folders; 2 tubes; 2 frames.
Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel is an advocate for the arts, interviewer, documentarian, teacher, political organizer, and resident of New York City. Her collection comprises research files, correspondence, audio and video recordings, printed materials, photographs, scrapbooks, artifacts, and artwork, all deriving from Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel's books, educational programming, interviews, public art installations, and exhibits centering on the arts, architecture, and historic preservation in the United States. The materials highlight her work with many arts and political organizations and her appointments to committees such as the Commission for Cultural Affairs and the New York Landmarks Preservation Commission. Topics include: art and architecture in the 20th century; gender and society; historic preservation; media and society; social conditions in Slovakia during her husband's ambassadorship there; U.S. politics and public policy, particularly related to the Democratic Party; women and the arts; women's rights; and many others. Early materials dating from 1929 to 1965 document her family history and early personal life. The collection also includes some materials concerning her husband, Carl Spielvogel, whose papers are also in the Rubenstein Library. Over one hundred of her television interviews with notable artists and other figures have been digitized by the Diamonstein-Spielvogel Video Archive at Duke University and are available online.
Access Restrictions
Access restricted. Access to this collection requires the written permission of the donor. Please contact Research Services for information about how to request permission.
Original audiovisual and electronic media are closed to use; use copies are available unless noted otherwise in the collection guide. All researchers requesting copies of audiovisual materials from the collection for purposes other than private study and research are required to present written permission from the donor approving the request.
Due to size and complexity, all audiovisual materials are described in the Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Audiovisual Materials Collection, a separate collection guide.
Digital use copies and files in this collection have been migrated to a library server unless otherwise noted, and can be accessed on-site in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services prior to visiting the library.
Provenance
The Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 1988 to 2020.
Collection Overview
Spanning 1876 to 2020, with the bulk of the materials dating from 1950 to the 2010s, the Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Collection documents the life and career of a pioneering advocate for art, architecture, historical preservation, and public policy. The collection comprises over 650 boxes of research files, correspondence, printed materials, photographs, memorabilia, artifacts, and artwork, all stemming from Diamonstein-Spielvogel's long career and her prolific output of books, educational programming, interviews, public art installations, and exhibits. The materials highlight her work with many arts and political organizations and her appointments to committees such as the Commission for Cultural Affairs and the New York Landmarks Preservation Commission. Over one hundred of her television interviews with notable artists and other figures have been digitized by the Diamonstein-Spielvogel Video Archive at Duke University.
Topics covered by the materials in this collection include broad categories such as art and architecture in the 20th century; historic preservation and the protection of cultural property; media and society; social conditions, women's rights and the arts in Slovakia during her husband's ambassadorship there; U.S. and overseas politics, particularly related to the Democratic Party; U.S. public policy, with a focus on the arts; the built environment; women and the arts; gender issues and women's rights; travel abroad; and many others. Early materials dating from 1929 to 1965 - chiefly correspondence, writings, and photographs - document family history, her education, and her earliest career in teaching. Other early dates in the collection refer to reproductions of 19th century images chiefly found in exhibit and research files.
The collection is divided into series: Correspondence, Writings, Personal Files, Political Files, Professional Files, Art and Architecture Project Files, Art and Design Project Files, Historic Preservation Project Files, Scrapbooks and Visual Arts Materials.
Taken as a whole, the collection offers rich documentation on the evolution of art and architecture in the U.S., the development of adaptive reuse and landmarks legislation, the relationship of public policy to the arts, and the interplay between public policy and the built environment. Materials from Diamonstein-Spielvogel's personal and research files also document the changing roles of men and women in the United States, and the development of U.S. gender studies; not only did she write on the subject, but her own experiences reveal aspects of women in the workforce, in politics and activist movements, and in positions of authority. Additionally, because of her work for the White House and the Democratic Party, the collection offers insights into 20th century U.S. politics, nationally and in her home state of New York.
Biographical Note
Throughout her career, Dr. Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel has served as a leading voice on some of the defining urban issues of our time, especially preservation of the historic built environment. She is a pioneering advocate of the arts, with interests in architecture, design and public policy. The first Director of Cultural Affairs for New York City, she brought the first public art to Bryant Park in 1967, and the first public performance by the Metropolitan Opera to Central Park. She was the longest-serving Landmarks Preservation Commissioner in the city's history, spanning the administrations of Mayors Lindsay, Beame, Koch, Dinkins and Giuliani from 1972 to 1987. She has also served as the Commissioner of the New York City Arts/Public Design Commission and of the New York City Cultural Commission, as the Chair of the New York City Landmarks Preservation Foundation (1987-1995), and since 1995 has been the Chair of the Historic Landmarks Preservation Center.
Diamonstein-Spielvogel has served under four presidential administrations. As part of the Johnson staff, she helped create the White House Fellows and Presidential House Scholars Programs, and the White House Festival of the Arts. She was appointed by President Reagan to the board of the U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum in Washington, D.C.; and by President Clinton to the U.S. Commission of Fine Arts, where she was elected the first woman vice chair in its more than 100-year history. In 2010, President Obama appointed her a commissioner of the American Battle Monuments Commission. She was named the vice chair of the New York State Council on the Arts in 2008 and chair in 2016. In 2012, she was appointed to advise the Port Authority on the integration of public art and architecture into the World Trade Center site. Diamonstein-Spielvogel also has been active in many state and national Democratic campaigns.
Diamonstein-Spielvogel received her doctorate with honors from New York University, and honorary doctorates from the Maryland Institute College of Art, Baltimore, MD; Longwood University, Longwood, VA; and the Pratt Institute, Brooklyn NY. She is the author of twenty books and numerous magazine and newspaper articles and has served as curator of seven international museum exhibitions; in 2013 an exhibit based on her latest book, Landmarks of New York, Vol. V, traveled to 14 cities throughout New York State.
She has served as interviewer/producer of nine television series for the Arts & Entertainment Network in addition to numerous programs for other national networks; many of her interviews with artists, architects, designers, and other notables have been digitized and made available on iTunes and YouTube as part of the Duke University Video Archive. In October 2010, Duke initiated the Diamonstein-Spielvogel Visiting Filmmaker Series to address contemporary issues of social, political, economic, and cultural urgency from a global perspective.
Diamonstein-Spielvogel has served on the boards of numerous national and local institutions and organizations, including recent service in support of the Fresh Air Fund, the Drawing Committee of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the Acquisitions Committee of the Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum, and the N.Y. Museum of Modern Art. She is a founding director of the Highline in New York City and the Trust for the National Mall in Washington, D.C. She has served on many boards including the American Council on the Arts, the White House Endowment Fund, the Municipal Art Society, the Landmarks Conservancy and B.A.M.
Diamonstein-Spielvogel has received numerous awards and honors, including an award from H.E.L.P. in 2001 and lifetime achievement awards from Partners for Livable Places in Washington, D.C. and the Citizens Committee of New York. She also received the Legend designation by the Pratt Institute, Landmarks Lion by the Historic Districts Council in 2010, and tje Elly Award honoring outstanding women leaders in 2012. In fall 2012 she was the recipient of the John Jay Heritage Award.
She is married to international business executive and former U.S. Ambassador to the Slovak Republic, Carl Spielvogel, whose papers are housed in the Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising and Marketing History at Duke University, and she resides in New York City.
Collection Arrangement
Within series, subseries are predominantly arranged alphabetically, with some subseries and files arranged chronologically.
Later additions have been sorted and boxed annually as they arrive, with file titles inserted into the guide where they topically or chronologically would fall. This results in box numbers appearing scattered within some of the collection's file lists or series.
Related Material
Diamonstein-Spielvogel Video Archive
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Additional materials related to Dr. Diamonstein-Spielvogel's contributions to historic preservation and the arts can be found in the New York State Archives.
Separated Materials
Due to size and complexity, all time-based media (recordings, compact disks, audiocassettes, videocassettes, film, etc.) from the Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Collection have been moved to the Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Audiovisual Materials Collection (RL-10006-AV).
Scrapbooks; Graphic arts -- United States; DVDs; CD-ROMs; Photographs; Machine-readable records; Political campaigns -- United States.; Federal Aid to the arts; Microcassettes; Audiocassettes; Oral histories (document genre); Slides (photographs); Fashion and art.; Black-and-white photographs; Public art -- United States.; Audiotapes; Celebrities -- United States -- Interviews; Decorative arts -- United States.; Cultural artifacts.; United States -- Cultural policy; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs; Women and the arts.; Contact sheets; Television and art.; Negatives (photographs); Slovakia -- Social conditions.; Historic preservation -- United States; Posters; Historic districts -- Conservation and restoration.; Videotapes; Film; New York (N.Y.) -- History; Women's rights -- United States; Interior decoration -- United States.; Artists -- United States -- Interviews; Arts and society -- United States; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Architecture -- United States.; Art and state -- United States.; Artists -- United States -- Correspondence; Diamonstein-Spielvogel, Barbaralee; New York (N.Y.). Landmarks Preservation Commission.; Spielvogel, Carl.; Democratic Party (U.S.)
- Correspondence, 1950-2020; undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series predominantly consists of Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel's incoming correspondence but also contains some drafts and copies of materials sent by Diamonstein-Spielvogel. The content generally centers on the logistics, planning, research, and creative energy behind her work, and the personal and professional relationships with friends, political figures, and business and project partners. There is a large overlap between personal and professional content.
  The earliest correspondence from the 1950s consists mainly of personal letters and cards pertaining to her travels, early career efforts, her marriage, and daily life. The later correspondence contains a significant amount of correspondence from notable figures such as Hillary Rodham Clinton, Dale Chihuly, Mario Buatta, and Louise Nevelson, among others. Often accompanying the letters are clippings and photographs, as well as printed materials such as invitations, fliers, advertisements, and pamphlets. The majority of the correspondence from the 2010s is email printouts.
  Other series in the collection also contain large amounts of correspondence pertaining to specific projects, organizations, or other activities. Letters from family members and letters referring to her weddings, personal art collection, homes, and travels is also located in the Personal Files Series. Selected letters of importance are also mounted in scrapbooks housed in the Scrapbook Series.
  - Chronological files, 1950-1962 (Box 1)
  - Chronological files, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Chronological files, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Chronological files, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Chronological files, 1966 (Box 5)
    Includes 1966 pamphlet Know Your Rights, published by U.S. Dept. of Labor.
  - Chronological files, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Chronological files, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Chronological files, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Chronological files, 1968 (Box 9)
  - Chronological files, 1968-1969 (Box 10)
  - Chronological files, 1969 (Box 11)
  - Chronological files, 1969 (Box 12)
  - Chronological files, Approximately 1960s (Box 12)
  - Chronological files, 1970 (Box 12)
  - Chronological files, 1970 (Box 13)
  - Chronological files, 1970-1971 (Box 14)
  - Chronological files, 1971 (Box 15)
  - Chronological files, 1972 (Box 16)
  - Chronological files, 1973 (Box 17)
  - RSVPs and correspondence to Louise Nevelson for dinner in honor of Barbaralee Diamonstein, 1973 (Box 18)
  - Chronological files, 1974 (Box 19)
  - Chronological files, 1975 (Box 20)
  - Chronological files, 1975-1976 (Box 21)
  - Chronological files, 1976 (Box 22)
  - Chronological files, 1977 (Box 23)
  - Chronological files, 1978 (Box 24)
  - Chronological files, 1978-1979 (Box 25)
  - Chronological files, Approximately 1970s (Box 25)
  - Chronological files, Approximately 1970s (Box 26)
  - Chronological files, 1980 (Box 26)
  - Chronological files, 1981 (Box 27)
  - Chronological files, 1981-1982 (Box 28)
  - Chronological files, 1982-1983 (Box 29)
  - Chronological files, 1983-1986 (Box 30)
  - Chronological files, 1987-1988 (Box 31)
  - Chronological files, 1989 (Box 32)
  - Chronological files, 1989 (Box 33)
  - Chronological files, Approximately 1980s (Box 33)
  - Chronological files, 1990 (Box 33)
  - Chronological files, 1990-1991 (Box 34)
  - Chronological files, 1991 (Box 35)
  - Chronological files, 1992 (Box 36)
  - Chronological files, 1992-1993 (Box 37)
  - Chronological files, 1993-1994 (Box 38)
  - Chronological files, 1994 (Box 39)
  - Chronological files, 1994 (Box 40)
  - Chronological files, 1995 (Box 41)
  - Chronological files, 1995 (Box 42)
  - Chronological files, 1996-1997 (Box 43)
  - Chronological files, 1998 (Box 44)
  - Chronological files, 1998-1999 (Box 45)
  - Chronological files, 1999 (Box 46)
  - Chronological files, Approximately 1990s (Box 46)
  - Chronological files, 2000; 2 folders (Box 46)
  - Chronological files, 2001-2002; 4 folders (Box 47)
  - Chronological files, 2002-2003 (Box 48)
  - Chronological files, 2003 (Box 49)
  - Chronological files, 2003-2004 (Box 50)
  - Chronological files, 2004 (Box 51)
  - Chronological files, 2004-2005 (Box 52)
  - Chronological files, 2005 (Box 53)
  - Chronological files, 2005 (Box 54)
  - Chronological files, 2005 (Box 55)
  - Chronological files, 2006 (Box 55)
  - Chronological files, 2006-2007 (Box 56)
  - Chronological files, 2006-2007 (Box 74)
  - Chronological files, 2007-2008 (Box 57)
  - Chronological files, 2008 (Box 58)
  - Chronological files, 2008 (Box 74)
  - Chronological files, 2009; 4 folders (Box 58)
  - Chronological files, 2009 (Box 74)
  - Chronological files, Approximately 2000s (Box 59)
  - Chronological files, 2010 (Box 59)
  - Chronological files, 2010 (Box 74)
  - Chronological files, 2010-2011 (Box 60)
  - Chronological files, 2011 (Box 61)
  - Chronological files, 2011 (Box 74)
  - Chronological files, 2011-2012 (Box 62)
  - Chronological files, 2012 (Box 63)
  - Chronological files, 2012 (Box 646)
  - Chronological files, 2012 (Box 65)
  - Chronological files, 2012 (Box 66)
  - Chronological files, 2012 (Box 74)
  - Chronological files, 2013; 3 folders (Box 65)
  - Chronological files, 2013; 2 folders (Box 74)
  - Chronological files, 2013 January-June (Box 66)
  - Chronological files, 2013 July-December; 7 folders (Box 607)
  - Cards, 2013 April-December; 2 folders (Box 68)
  - Chronological files, 2014; 1 folder (Box 68)
  - Chronological files, 2014-2015; 7 folders (Box 615)
  - Chronological files, 2015 (Box 71)
  - Chronological files, 2015-2016; 7 folders (Box 77)
  - Chronological files, 2016; 6 folders (Box 71)
  - Chronological files, 2016; 4 folders (Box 72)
  - Chronological files, 2015-2018; 5 folders (Box 73)
  - Chronological files, 2017 (Box 648)
  - Chronological files, 2018; 12 Files (Box 648)
  - Chronological files, 2019; 5 folders (Box 649)
  - Chronological files, 2019; 9 folders (Box 653, Box 654)
  - Philanthropy, 2016-2017 (Box 73)
  - Cards and holidays, 2016-2017; 2 folders (Box 72)
  - Cards, approximately 2018 (Box 648)
  - Invitations, 2006-2016; 14 folders (Box 74)
  - Invitations, 2015-2016; 4 folders (Box 71)
  - Event calendars, 2016 (Box 71)
  - Chronological files, Approximately 2010s (Box 65)
  - Undated correspondence, 3 folders (Box 68)
- Writings, 1953-2015; undated
  - American Bicentennial, 1967-1979; undated; 1
    Folders house drafts, notes, correspondence, photographs, clippings, and printed material stemming from Diamonstein-Spielvogel's role in organizing the celebration of the American Bicentennial in New York City in 1976.
    - American Issues Forum, 1967-1974 (Box 645)
    - American Issues Forum, 1967-1974 (Box 64)
    - American Issues Forum brochures, 1974 (Box 175)
    - American Issues Forum photographs, 1975 (Box 64)
    - American Issues Forum, Showboat, 1972-1979 (Box 64)
    - American Issues Forum Calendar draft, 1974 (Box 76)
    - Clippings, correspondence, other printed materials, 1974 (Box 64)
    - Clippings, correspondence, other printed materials, 1974-1978 (Box 64)
    - Meetings, reports, notes, other printed materials, 1974 (Box 67)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, contract for bicentennial calendar and catalogue, 1974 (Box 67)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, correspondence and notes, 1975 (Box 67)
    - Program, newsletter, other printed materials, 1975 (Box 67)
    - Art research, 1974 (Box 67)
    - Background from National Endowment for the Humanities, 1974; 2 folders (Box 67)
    - Brochure, undated (Box 624)
    - Budgets, 1974 (Box 624)
    - Cohen-Queens Lithography, 1974 (Box 624)
    - Deborah, 1974-1976; 2 folders (Box 624)
    - Expenses, 1974 (Box 624)
    - Handwritten notes, 1974-1975 (Box 624)
    - Helen, 1974-1976; 4 folders (Box 624)
    - Illustrations, 1974 (Box 69)
    - Kriss, 1974 (Box 69)
    - Margaret, 1974 (Box 69)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, contract amendment and draft, 1975 (Box 69)
    - New York Bicentennial Commission, correspondence and notes, 1974 (Box 69)
    - Original of 8/28 draft, 1974 (Box 69)
    - Original 10/4 draft, 1974; 3 folders (Box 69)
    - Outline of issues, 1975 (Box 69)
    - Project materials, 1974-1976 (Box 70)
    - Quote permissions, undated (Box 70)
    - Quotes, 1974 (Box 70)
    - Rewrites, 1974 (Box 70)
    - Selected quotes and incidents, 1975-1976 (Box 70)
    - Text, 1975-1976; folders 1-3 of 4 (Box 70)
    - Text, 1975-1976; folder 4 of 4 (Box 80)
    - Texts I and II, 1975; 3 folders (Box 80)
  - Columbia Broadcasting System (CBS), 1961-1980; 2
    Includes drafts, notes, correspondence, photographs, clippings, and printed material deriving from Diamonstein-Spielvogel's writings for CBS. Recordings corresponding with Playboy Mystique are located in the Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel Audiovisual Materials Collection. General working files for CBS are located in the Organizations Subseries of the Professional Files Series; other CBS materials are scattered throughout the collection with their corresponding projects. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Books/poetry, 1974-1980 (Box 80)
    - Lamp Unto My Feet, 1974-1977 (Box 80)
    - Music, 1977-1980 (Box 80)
    - Playboy Mystique, 1961-1974; folder 1 of 3 (Box 80)
    - Playboy Mystique, 1961-1974; folders 2-3 of 3 (Box 81)
  - Corcoran Gallery, 1968; 1986-2006; 3
    Manuscript materials related to interviews Diamonstein-Spielvogel produced for the Corcoran Gallery, consisting chiefly of notes and drafts with some clippings and correspondence. Arranged alphabetically by interviewee's last name.
    - Brooke Astor interview, 1986-1991 (Box 81)
    - David Hockney interview, 1991-1992 (Box 81)
    - Eric Fischl interview, 1989-1995 (Box 81)
    - Robert Graham interview, 1994-1997 (Box 81)
    - Jack Lenor Larson interview, 1996 (Box 81)
    - Roy Lichtenstein interview, 1994-2006 (Box 81)
    - Larry Rivers interview, 1997 (Box 81)
    - David Salle, Corcoran/Rogers Memorial interview, 1986-1995 (Box 75)
    - Frank Stella interview, 1968-1999 (Box 75)
  - Good Housekeeping (magazine), 1971-1972; 4
    Contains drafts, notes, correspondence, interviews, and clippings for two articles Diamonstein-Spielvogel wrote for Good Housekeeping Magazine.
    - Here Come the Brides, 1971 (Box 75)
    - Here Come the Brides, memo and layout proof sheets, 1971 (Box 175)
    - Sarah Miles, "Another Divine Sarah,", 1971-1972 (Box 75)
  - Harper's Bazaar (magazine), 1966-2013; bulk 1969-1971; 5
    Contains drafts, notes, correspondence, interviews, clippings, photographs, and printed matter pertaining to the work Diamonstein-Spielvogel did for Harper's Bazaar including general administrative files, interviews, articles, and proposals. Materials for larger Harper's projects including The Decade of the Sixties, Emphasis, and Singular Voices: 100 Women in Touch with our Time are grouped under each subheading.
    One of her largest and most comprehensive articles dealing with women in American society, Singular Voices: 100 Women in Touch with our Time contains many similarly titled subheadings because the article went through numerous title changes during its creation. This article grew into Diamonstein-Spielvogel's book, Open Secrets, and corresponding materials are located in the Open Secrets Subseries of the Writings Series.
    Arranged alphabetically by folder title, except Emphasis, a recurring column on art and culture, which is arranged chronologically.